**Imad Ali** 

Phone: (347) 824 1258

Email: imadmali@gmail.com

Website: http://www.imadali.net

LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/imadmali

GitHub https://github.com/imadmali

#### **Profile**

Experienced Data Science professional with expertise in R, Python, SQL, Git, Bash, Stata, Mathematica, and AWS. Fluent in Stan (an implementation of Bayesian statistical inference in R) and have a working knowledge of Theano (deep learning Python library). Exceptional communicator to individuals with quantitative and non-quantitative backgrounds. Current research involves Bayesian inference and computational methods in Statistics. Areas of proficiency include:

\* Data Mining

\* Machine Learning

\* Regression Analysis

\* Bayesian Statistics

- \* Classification/Clustering Analysis
- \* Institutional Research

# **Professional Experience**

### The New School, Data Analyst, Provost's Office - Planning and Analytics

Jun 2015 - Jan 2016

- Developed nonlinear models to determine the effect of financial aid on student enrolment for graduate programs.
- Lead on the transition from a Python based data management system to a Visual Basic based system.
- Worked closely on developing data analytic and data management tools with the Director of Business Intelligence and Associate Provost.
- Identified flaws in existing processing software and updated Python dictionaries to amend these flaws.

### Al Jazeera, Media Data Consultant, Al Jazeera Sports

Aug 2015

- Provided insight on how to compare World Wrestling Entertainment's popularity against peer sports franchises and entertainment companies.
- Developed data visualizations of several entertainment company stock prices in R published in this article (http://bit.ly/1P8xtCV).

## New York Office of the Attorney General, Statistician, Civil Rights Bureau

Jun 2015 - Aug 2015

- Developed econometric models using Stata and R to model bank behavior in New York State using least squares, weighted least squares, and general linear (probability) models.
- Implemented odds ratio analyses and Fisher's exact test using Python to determine discriminatory lending practices by banks.
- Presented a business case to the Bureau Chief on the implementation of descriptive and inferential statistics in the department, and the availability and use of data relevant to the bureau's docket.

# Scottish Government, Assistant Economist, Office of the Chief Economic Adviser

Sep 2013 - Mar 2014

- · Led the department on weekly and monthly economic briefing (including ad hoc requests).
- Responsible for delivering and updating a weekly economic performance brief to the First Minister in under 6
  hours, which contained information from a diverse collection of government departments.

- Personally drafted a response to a Parliamentary Question on the performance of Scottish exports on behalf of the Finance Minister.
- Oversaw and facilitated the development of a report on Scotland's economic performance for the European Commission.
- Redesigned the departments briefing in order to meet Parliamentary standards and ensured briefing was prepared accurately and delivered on time.
- Collaborated with statisticians to update GDP, productivity, and labor market statistics for the First Minister and Finance Minister.

### **Academic Experience**

#### Columbia University, Teaching Assistant, Bayesian Statistics

Jan 2016 - Present

Teaching assistant for Bayesian Statistics for the Social Sciences taught by Dr Benjamin Goodrich.

## The New School, Research Assistant, Bayesian Networks

Jan 2016 - Present

Researching causal relationships and efficient learning using Bayesian Networks.

## The New School, Teaching Fellow, Quantitative Reasoning

Aug 2015 - Dec 2015

- Taught a core course on applied mathematics and statistics to a class of over 20 students.
- Topics included Financial Mathematics, Statistical Inference, Probability Theory, and Data Analysis.

#### **Relevant Courses**

Neural Networks and Deep Learning (Columbia University)
 Bayesian Data Analysis (Columbia University)
 Data Mining (Columbia University)
 Applied Econometrics (New York University)
 Panel Data Analysis (New York University)
 Advanced Topics in Vector Calculus (The New School)

## **Education**

Columbia University; New York, USA

MA Statistics (2018)

Edinburgh University; Scotland, UK

MS Economics (2013)

Leeds University; England, UK

BA Joint Honors Economics and Politics (2012)